In today's video, we are going to make
flavor extracts using a non-alcoholic
preparation
and today is blueberry.
[Music]
People love to shout about alcohol in
ice creams and food and how you can't
give it to kids, blah blah blah. Now,
don't take this out of context. Vanilla
extract has been used in cakes and
baking for
as long as it's existed and you give
those to your kids every day of the
week. So why is it a problem when you
put it in ice cream? It isn't. There is
an alternative and that is using
vegetable glycerin or glycerin based
extracts. Just so happens that most of
the extracts up until the last 5 years
available in supermarkets have been
alcohol- based. They don't often say
that, but they are. So, now the glycerin
types are becoming more popular. It does
the same thing. Doesn't really make any
difference. So, here we go. Vegetable
glycerin extracts. You can buy vegetable
glycerin in a lot of places. Don't think
you can buy it in supermarkets yet. You
can buy it on Amazon in whatever country
it is you're in. Um, you can buy it in
specialized shops as well, baking shops,
you know, kitchen shops, that kind of
places. Um, you will also be able to buy
it wherever you buy your traditional
extract, so vanilla extract, etc. Um,
now vegetable glycerin,
it's it's it's a bit of a wording thing
there. Here's two different types. This
is Lauran vegetable glycerin. This came
from Michaels, which is a craft store.
Now, Lauran, obviously, is food grade.
Now, this is now solutions from Amazon.
It's identical in every single way. Is
this sold as a food preparation one? And
this isn't sold as a food preparation
one. This is organic and 100% vegetable
glycerin as is this. I don't know if
this is organic. Doesn't say. But it is
also sold for use in skin care. It's
used in moisturizing creams and stuff
like that. So, for me personally, as
long as I'm buying 100% vegetable
glycerin in an organic form, if it's not
coming in food grade, then I'm happy to
use this. You make that choice. If you
desperately want to get food grade, then
source food grade vegetable glycerin.
So, with that in mind,
there's a couple of things we need to
do. And that is we need to change the
solution slightly because vegetable
glycerin is too thick to extract the
flavor profiles from your food. And in
this case are frozen. They're not frozen
at all. They are
freeze-dried
blueberries. Let's get these out of the
pack.
Slightly squishy again, just like
raisins. They obviously don't smell like
raisins. So that's what we're going to
use. Now to extract the flavor compounds
from this, we need our solution to be
able to permeate in through the flesh
and withdraw. Vegetable glycerin is just
too thick really to enable that to
happen. Alcohol, so ethanol, which is
what 90% of food extracts are made with,
is thin enough to permeate and it does a
much better job actually of extracting
that. So we have to give it a bit of a
helping hand. So, what we're going to do
is we're going to take a small pan and
we're going to put our glycerin
in there. So, in that goes, as you can
see, it's pretty thick. It's kind of, if
you've never seen this, it's like a
thick syrup consistency. So, this is all
going to go in here. Going to put the
whole lot. I'm going to put all of this
in here as well. There are a lot of
other uses for glycerin. It's supposedly
good for your skin and everything. So,
here we go. This is the consistency. So,
as you can see, it's quite thick stuff.
Now, in there, these are both the same
size. They're 4 oz, 4 fl ounces, 120 ml.
So, 240 ml, that's about a cup's worth
of vegetable glycerin. We need to thin
that down. So, we're going to add a/4 of
a cup of water into that. Yeah. 1/4 of a
cup being, you know, about 60 ml. Let's
add some of that in here. Now,
you don't have to be super accurate with
it, but what we are doing is we're
changing the viscosity of our glycerin
so that it can permeate into that fruit
flesh or whatever it is that you're
making an extract out of. So, now that
we've got that good stir, it kind of
goes this weird slimy kind of
consistency for the first few minutes.
That is fine. So, now we are going to
get our blueberries in here. How many do
we have in here? This is 120 g, so just
4 and a/4 oz in weight. Now, you don't
have to put all that in there, but it
will make it much stronger. So, I'm
going to put the whole pack.
I got these off of Amazon. Lots of
different variations. You can, if you
get access to blueberries and you have a
dehydrator, then make it make them
yourselves. It's you you can do this
with fresh. You can reduce the amount of
water that you add to your glycerin if
you're using fresh fruit. There's
already water in there. Now, what we're
going to do is we're going to pop this
on the hob and we're just going to
gently heat this. And we're going to
gently heat this for at least an hour.
So, what I suggest you do is you get it
up to nearly boiling point. So, you
know, 80 to 90 centrade, 180, 190
Fahrenheit, something like that. Then
turn your heat down onto the lowest
setting and then let it tick over for an
hour. Once that's done, we'll come back.
So, after a really good heating again,
just ticking over on the lowest setting
for about an hour, we've got this really
dark, almost black kind of liquor going
on in there with our blueberries. We
still have a long time before this is
ready. So, what we need to do is get
this in a container that is airtight.
So, a good Tupperware container or, you
know, a bottle or something like this. I
mean, this is ginormous, but you know,
something along those lines. And what
we're going to do is we're simply going
to pour that into our container.
Pop the lid on and we're going to leave
this at room temperature for about a
month. Obviously, I'm not going to make
you wait a month for this. So, here's
some I made earlier. This was sat in the
fridge, refrigerator for just over a
month. Incredibly strong smell.
strong strong strong blueberry taste. So
there's probably 250 ml um worth of
blueberry extract here if you use the
numbers that I use in this recipe. Do
the same for any freeze dried fruit and
just strain it when you put it in here.
So this um I use
these little doodads
cheesecloth. Let it strain through and
then you get this incredible extract
that you can use in ice creams, coffees,
baking, whatever it is you want to use
it as. So there we go. A nice simple
blueberry extract, non-alcoholbased,
so glycerin based recipe. Let me know if
you want to see me make more extracts.
Quite happy to do it. I love doing this
kind of stuff. Not every extract is the
same. Things like cherries is an
interesting one. So maybe I'll do a
cherry extract next time. So thanks very
much for watching. Don't forget to like
and subscribe and I will see you next
time.
[Music]